<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Rodrigo Favarete]]></title><description><![CDATA[I like to show my work the right way, with the right info, outside the controlled environment of 
    the social networks. So I created this blog page, where I can add everything I think worth showing.]]></description><link>https://favarete.art</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 22:10:48 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Nutshell]]></title><description><![CDATA[Nutshell is the seventh, and last, design from the We are Animals I series, a
series of pieces portraying great minds wronged by humanity’s…]]></description><link>https://favarete.art/nutshell/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://favarete.art/nutshell/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nutshell&lt;/em&gt; is the seventh, and last, design from the &lt;em&gt;We are Animals I&lt;/em&gt; series, a
series of pieces portraying great minds wronged by humanity’s thoughts.
This piece shows Rosalind Franklin, English chemist and X-ray crystallographer
whose work was central to the understanding of the molecular structures of DNA,
RNA and viruses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Franklin decided that she wanted to be a scientist when she was 15, against
her parents’ wishes, who saw no future for her in this male-dominated area.
Six years after the decision, she graduated in Natural Sciences from Newnham
College, Cambridge University’s women-only college. Four years later, she
earned her Ph.D. and, in the following year, became a researcher, analyzing
the physical structure of charred materials using x-rays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She used the same X-ray technique to later conduct the entire study that
allowed her to determine the helical structure of the DNA molecule. With
her observations and notes, biochemists James Dewey Watson and Francis Crick,
along with the head of the laboratory where she worked, Maurice Wilkins,
confirmed the double structure of the DNA molecule and thus won the Nobel
Prize for Medicine in 1962. However, Rosalind did not take any credit for
her own research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1950s, women were still significantly undervalued in academia;
they were segregated to exclusively female and non-scientific spaces. For
example, they were not allowed to use campus restaurants, and many
establishments did not even allow them to enter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science and everyday life cannot and should not be separated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Rosalind Franklin (1920 - 1958)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Franklin died young, aged 37, from late-discovered cancer. When she died
in 1958, the scientist had received no recognition for her work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years, some letters were revealed; they showed conversations between
Crick, Watson, and Wilkins. The scientists called her a “witch” and conspired
against her presence in the laboratory. The letters they exchanged also show
that they were fully aware that Rosalind’s research was the fundamental piece
for the Nobel prize. Only in the 1960s, she comes to be recognized by the
scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Favarete&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cyber Defense]]></title><description><![CDATA[Cyber Defense is the sixth design from the We are Animals I series, a
series of pieces portraying great minds wronged by humanity’s thoughts…]]></description><link>https://favarete.art/cyber-defence/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://favarete.art/cyber-defence/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cyber Defense&lt;/em&gt; is the sixth design from the &lt;em&gt;We are Animals I&lt;/em&gt; series, a
series of pieces portraying great minds wronged by humanity’s thoughts.
This piece shows Alan Turing, English mathematician, computer scientist,
logician, cryptanalyst, philosopher, and theoretical biologist. One of the
most profound minds of the twenty century, best known as the father of
theoretical computer science and artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turing always showed signs of his above-average intelligence. In addition,
he was an avid reader of physics and math books. In one of his articles,
published at the age of 24, he talked about computable numbers; it was in
this article that he devised a mechanical process that could tell when a
logical procedure could be proven or not. This procedure is known today as
the Turing Machine, a hypothetical device that would change roles as needed.
We learned some of the fundamental logic of algorithms from this machine.
We also learned what would become all the modern computing we know today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another impressive achievement he is remembered for is the techniques for
speeding the breaking of German ciphers during the second world war. Turing
played a crucial role in cracking intercepted coded messages that enabled
the Allies to defeat the Nazis in many critical engagements. Some historians
estimated that his work shortened the war in Europe by more than two years
and saved over 14 million lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science is a differential equation. Religion is a boundary condition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Alan Turing - Epigram to Robin Gandy (1954)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another well-known fact about Turing is when he almost married a teammate,
but she chose not to move on when he told her he was gay. Later, in 1952,
after having his home broken into by a friend of a man with whom he became
involved, he reported the case to the police. He was arrested after admitting
his sexual orientation to the authorities and tried under the Labouchere
Amendment of 1885, which considered it illegal to be homosexual. Possibly
because of his importance to the government, he was offered freedom on the
condition that he undergo “treatment” with injections of synthetic estrogen,
chemical castration with a female hormone that caused several side effects.
Turing ended up accepting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two years after this event, Turing was found dead of cyanide ingestion. He
was only 41 years old and allegedly poisoned an apple and ate to end his own
life after being persecuted for being gay, losing his job, and financial
conditions. However, some people, among them Turing’s mother, argue that he
probably accidentally poisoned himself while dealing with chemicals in his
home laboratory and deny that his death was by suicide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was only in 1967 that the laws of the United Kingdom stopped making
homosexuality a crime. However, it was only in 2017 that a law lifted the
conviction of all those unjustly persecuted men before the end of the
homophobic legislation. The “Turing law” was named after the most famous
victim of institutionalized homophobia in England.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Favarete&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Prison]]></title><description><![CDATA[Prison is the fifth design from the We are Animals I series, a
series of pieces portraying great minds wronged by humanity’s thoughts.
This…]]></description><link>https://favarete.art/prison/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://favarete.art/prison/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 May 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prison&lt;/em&gt; is the fifth design from the &lt;em&gt;We are Animals I&lt;/em&gt; series, a
series of pieces portraying great minds wronged by humanity’s thoughts.
This piece shows Camile Claudel, a French sculptor, best known for her bronze
and marble depictions of figures. She died in relative obscurity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Camile faced many difficulties throughout her life, even being barred from art
schools such as the École des Beaux Arts just for being a woman. But, without
giving up, she ended up studying at one of the few spaces that accepted women
at the time, the Académie Colarossi. And in 1882, she managed to set up a studio
with other women and produced her first sculptures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of her mentors was Auguste Rodin, another sculptor. She began a problematic
relationship with him in 1884 but never actually lived with him, who only used
her as a model and lover, always reluctant to end her twenty-year relationship
with Rose Beuret. The relationship ended in 1892, but her reputation was still
associated with the image of the sculptor. She left the relationship with an
intense depression that accompanied her throughout her life. The end also caused
her to suffer massive boycotts in the artistic scene, which led her to increase
isolation and poverty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Camille was a genius of sculpture but only received due recognition after her
death. The end of her life was in a psychiatric hospital, hospitalized by her
family, who claimed she was demented for destroying many of her works and acting
paranoid, accusing Rodin of stealing her ideas and leading a conspiracy to kill her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am scared; I don’t know what is going to happen to me. What was the point
of working so hard and of being talented, to be rewarded like this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Camile Claudel (1864 - 1943)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hospitalization took place after her father’s death in 1913. Perhaps he was
the only person in her family who approved her career choice and helped her in
some way throughout her life, besides supporting her financially several times.
The hospital management stated several times that the artist could return to
social life because she was lucid, although she had mental outbursts. Still,
her mother always refused to release her and forbade her to receive visits or
even correspondence from someone who wasn’t her brother, the very one who had
committed her. Some historians speculate that her brother, also an artist, felt
overshadowed by Camile’s art and used his internment to get her out of his way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She was an artist crushed by the society of her time. It’s unfortunate to know
that, despite the achievements of women in the last century, we are still in a
sexist world where it is common to see women living similar problems like the
ones in Camiles’ life. It is also fair to think that many of these stories are
hidden, a lot of these stories are happening right now, but we will never know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Favarete&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Metamorphosis]]></title><description><![CDATA[Metamorphosis is the fourth design from the We are Animals I series, a 
series of pieces portraying great minds wronged by humanity’s…]]></description><link>https://favarete.art/metamorphosis/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://favarete.art/metamorphosis/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Metamorphosis&lt;/em&gt; is the fourth design from the &lt;em&gt;We are Animals I&lt;/em&gt; series, a
series of pieces portraying great minds wronged by humanity’s thoughts.
This piece shows Vincent van Gogh, the famous Post-Impressionist painter.
Even today, some people are still not too familiar with the details about
Vincent, mainly that he was never recognized in life by his genius. He was
commercially unsuccessful during his lifetime, and he was considered a
madman and a failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, we can say that Vincent was ahead of his time even in his mental
conditions since today we face more and more problems with depression,
anxiety, and other diseases considered the &lt;em&gt;diseases of modernity&lt;/em&gt;. It
was also typical that he would often neglect his physical health, eat
properly, and drink heavily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He started painting later in his life, when he had 27 or 28 years, after
failing at multiple other jobs. Then, after a tormented life that led to
isolation, he died virtually anonymously by shooting himself in the chest.
There was still an attempt to help him, but he could not resist the wounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps we only know of his life because of the roughly 750 letters he wrote
to his brother Theo, with whom he had a gigantic connection, and because of
his sister-in-law, Jo van Gogh-Bonger, who did everything she could to promote
his work after his death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you hear a voice within you say ‘you cannot paint,’ then by all means
paint, and that voice will be silenced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Vincent van Gogh - Letter to Theo van Gogh (28 October 1883)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Van Gogh’s life makes me think about the place of art today. How many people,
how many great artists are creating unique concepts but are still, and will
always be, unknown, lost in some social media, ignored by the algorithms and
by the galleries. We are constantly trying to make something meaningful in
our modern world, with our work lost in the middle of tons of artificial
content. Van Gogh was ignored and underestimated by the galleries and artists
of his time. It seems to be the fate for most artists even today in this era
of communication filled with plastic information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Favarete&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[All the Eyes]]></title><description><![CDATA[All the eyes is the third design from the We are Animals I series, a series of pieces portraying great 
minds wronged by humanity’s thoughts…]]></description><link>https://favarete.art/all-the-eyes/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://favarete.art/all-the-eyes/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 May 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All the eyes&lt;/em&gt; is the third design from the &lt;em&gt;We are Animals I&lt;/em&gt; series, a series of pieces portraying great
minds wronged by humanity’s thoughts. This piece shows Abū al-ʿAlāʾ al-Maʿarrī, an Arab philosopher, poet,
and writer from the 10th century of the common era. He was a controversial rationalist of his time, using
reason as his primary source of truth and denning all religious and esoterical thinking, challenging work
in a very mythological-based generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Al-Maʿarrī became blind when four due to smallpox; later, he referred to himself as the &lt;em&gt;hostage of two prisons,&lt;/em&gt;
his blindness, and his home, which he rarely left. As he grew older, he traveled to some Syrian cities, learning by
heart the manuscripts and giving lectures on poetry and rhetoric. Al-Maʿarrī was a vegan and wrote some of what
most likely are the first mentions of a vegan worldview. He believed in the sanctity of life, urging that no living
creature should be harmed and opposing all killing of animals and the use of animal skins for clothing. He never
married and died in May 1057 in his hometown, aged 83, a very extreme age for his time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I No Longer Steal From Nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Al-Maʿarrī (c. early 1000)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the demonstrations of religious intolerance for its rational thinking happened in early 2013 when Islamist
militants in northwest Syria decapitated a statue of the poet, created in the 1940s by a young Syrian sculptor,
Fathi Mohammed.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something that inspires me a lot in Al-Maʿarrī works is the Luzūmīyāt, &lt;em&gt;Necessities&lt;/em&gt;, an extensive collection of
verses that contrasts from traditional pieces by its irregular structure together with the opinions it contains.
I always try to approach art in a distinctive form, outside common sense, since art, for me, is an idea that is an
inseparable part of a world in which reality is not directly accessible to the eye. Reality is a collection of
staggering layers, permanently inaccessible without rationality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Favarete&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Shadow of the Earth]]></title><description><![CDATA[The Shadow of the Earth is the second design from the We are Animals I series, a series of
pieces portraying great minds wronged by humanity…]]></description><link>https://favarete.art/the-shadow-of-the-earth/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://favarete.art/the-shadow-of-the-earth/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Shadow of the Earth&lt;/em&gt; is the second design from the &lt;em&gt;We are Animals I&lt;/em&gt; series, a series of
pieces portraying great minds wronged by humanity’s thoughts. This piece shows Suzanne Césaire.
She was born in Martinique, an overseas department of France located in the Caribbean Sea.
She was a French writer, teacher, theorist, anti-colonial, and an active feminist who participated
in the Union des Femmes Françaises. She published most of her work in the journal Tropiques,
which she co-founded during the authoritarian government of Marshal Philippe Pétain, an independent
ally of Nazi Germany during World War II. The journal established surrealism as a means of
cultural liberation and used the arts as a method of communicating political agendas without
the government’s censors knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Her affinity with surrealism led her to start a close relationship with another surrealist,
André Breton, with opened the way for her development of Afro-Surrealism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our surrealism will then deliver it the bread of its depths […] Colonial stupidity will be purified in the
blue welding flame. Our value as metal, our cutting edge of steel, our amazing communions will be recovered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Suzanne Césaire - Surrealism and Us (1943)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tropiques was the most influential Caribbean journal of its time and a foundational piece
in the development of Martiniquan literature. She played a crucial role in both the administrative
and intellectual roles of the platform, and yet despite her substantial written and editorial
contribution to the journal, two men, Aimé Césaire, her husband, and René Ménil, were cited as
the fundamental catalysts for the journal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Favarete&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Human Evolution]]></title><description><![CDATA[Human Evolution is the first design from the We are Animals I series, a series of 
pieces portraying great minds wronged by humanity’s…]]></description><link>https://favarete.art/human-evolution/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://favarete.art/human-evolution/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 02 May 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Human Evolution&lt;/em&gt; is the first design from the &lt;em&gt;We are Animals I&lt;/em&gt; series, a series of
pieces portraying great minds wronged by humanity’s thoughts. This piece shows Charles
Darwin. The English naturalist, known for his proposition that all species of life have
descended over time from common ancestors. Despite his widely accepted theory, with a
ton of evidence and considered a foundational concept in science, many people, most of
them religious people with creationist ideas, still reject his scientific genius and
knowledge, trying to keep their doctrines safe. Darwin ended his life as an agnostic,
as stated by himself in a letter to John Fordyce on May 7, 1879.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until today some people still claim that Darwin had reverted to Christianity on his
sickbed. However, the claims were all repudiated by Darwin’s children and have been
dismissed as false by historians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One point I consider worth mentioning, about respect for animals. Despite some evidence
pointing to the love Darwin has for animals, for example, his quote on &lt;em&gt;The Descent of Man
(1871)&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disinterested love for all living creatures, the most noble attribute of man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Charles Darwin - The Descent of Man (1871)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Darwin was not even remotely a vegetarian. On the contrary, he was even a member of
a social dining club called The Gluttons, who specialized in eating a strange meal at
his university, with lots of meat dishes. So, despite all the scientific knowledge and
insight, Darwin was also a person that died without respecting his subject of study
the way he should, as said by his own words. Furthermore, he can also be used as an
example of mistakes to be avoided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Favarete&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Liberation Through Art]]></title><description><![CDATA[Liberation Through Art is the first work from the Dispersions I series, a series of paintings exploring Uniform 
Lidimism. In this piece I…]]></description><link>https://favarete.art/liberation-through-art/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://favarete.art/liberation-through-art/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Liberation Through Art&lt;/em&gt; is the first work from the &lt;em&gt;Dispersions I&lt;/em&gt; series, a series of paintings exploring Uniform
Lidimism. In this piece I explored the divergent perspective as the main element to show the world of shadows where this
collection lives. The canvas is central, exploding to create the world around; to create everything, like an entity
who knows everything about myself, about my anguish and depression, and as a spectator who can show everything about
this entire world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This series is very personal and this piece was the starting point. I painted everything as fast as I could, like
the expressionists did in the past, but the scene I was looking was inside myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Rodrigo Favarete - 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This piece has 29.7 x 21 cm and was painted using my technique of Oil on Paper, in fact, this was the first time I
used this technique in a real piece of art outside my studies. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rodrigo Favarete&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>